hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of Holo talk
for the week of December 13
1998. I was going to actually take a
holiday but because of all the
happenings with the new laser pointer
discoveries I decided to hang in there
for another week to bring another report
to you I've been in the lab for a while
so I have some information on laser
pointer holography for you as you may
remember a few weeks ago Steve Michael
came on the show and told us that he had
created a four by five inch reflection
and Laser transmission hologram using a
laser pointer
and this created quite a stir
and I went out and got a laser pointer
on my own now he got one from the Edmond
scientific catalog I believe he paid 49
for it I found one at a drugstore called
Eckerd Drugs which is a subsidiary of
JCPenney so I imagine it's a national
drug store chain and I got mine for 7.99
650 nanometers 5 milliwatts so I bought
one brought it home got things set up
did a hologram and I was absolutely
surprised when I uh saw the results from
this 799 laser pointer so I went out and
I bought a bunch of other ones since
that time I have a number of different
things to update you on to possibly get
you started as well with laser winner
holography uh you know it's really funny
I was going over one of the old catalogs
from 1991 because I keep everything the
lowest price laser pointer in this 1991
catalog was a hundred and forty dollars
it was a three milliwatt operating at
670 nanometers that was their lowest
price and they had that exclamation
points uh next to that like you know wow
grab this now
they were still selling the small
handheld helium neon tubes these are
small helium neon battery operated
lasers that you could hold in the palm
of your hand
and they actually put out one milliwatt
a new price was 279 dollars
there were a few other pointers on the
page as well
none of them were very uh powerful I
don't believe any of them went over one
millilit to tell you the truth except
for that uh that lowest price one which
was around three uh a 0.9 milliwatt was
selling this is a pointer at 259 dollars
and there was another one on the page
that said solid state laser pointer
which to me a diode would be solid-state
laser so I'm not quite sure what that
was referring to but in any case that
was a half a milliwatt to one milliwatt
output at
670 nanometers at
for a half milliwatt to one milliwatt
laser pointer back in 1991.
369 dollars
and once again
the Hologram that I created was using a
five milliwatt 650 nanometer laser
pointer for seven dollars and ninety
nine cents now why is this such a big
deal obviously you're coming on the show
and you're listening to me talk about
this and you know I'm very excited about
it I am I'm just
beside myself I mean what a wonderful
time of the year to have a discovery
like this it's it's almost magical to me
I feel young like a kid again I'm back
in the lab working with things and
discovering things all over again and
you know holography is very magical uh
you you really get bit with the
holography bug when you get started with
holography and that's probably one of
the big things with this is the fact
that we really do need to bring more
people into holography but it's so
restrictive basically it boils down to
money that's what everything always
always boils down to and there are
places that sell Surplus and
manufacturers overruns lasers and
they're very good lasers I have one
myself which I use in my lab all the
time too but you're still looking at an
outlay an initial outlay of maybe a 150
to 200 dollars to get into the five
milliwatt range or so even if it were
only a 100 output of money you still
can't compare that to eight bucks
and that's what's really exciting about
this because that is the biggest outlay
that you make when you're beginning
hologography and you can't go any
further in holography until you take
that first step and begin it you have to
start and once you do start there is no
feeling on the face of this Earth
well maybe a couple
but no feeling on the face of this Earth
it compares to seeing that first
hologram that you've made once that's in
your system it's in your system and I've
been making holograms for years and
years and years and I still go down into
lab occasionally someone wants to have a
hologram made or I have workshops or
things like that
but it's basically the same thing for me
all the time it's been that way for
years but this is something brand new
and I'd also like to announce which I
don't think I have in my notes here and
I don't know how I miss that I'm also
running this uh laser pointer off of a
power supply that you can pick up at
just about any Radio Shack or a Best Buy
or any place that you see that sells the
AC to DC converters for walkmans
cassette players CD players and things
of that nature that usually run off of
batteries but you can also run them off
the house current this laser takes 4.5
volts
now it's Thursday night I'm doing the
show a little bit early
and I started this laser on the power
supply Sunday night and it's still going
it's still going so no cost of batteries
or anything anymore and it's very
inexpensive you know
um
and it's portable it it's small in size
it's because it is battery powered if
you don't want to run it off of a power
supply you can go and make Holograms
with no power is available I got an
email from someone and I won't say their
name because I'd like to get them on the
show and they're thinking about it so
I'll I don't want to scare them away
before I can even get them on the show
but it's a husband and wife team
and they go into caves and do holography
the formations that are in some of the
caves they take in their plates they
take in a helium neon laser and they lug
a large battery power supply which they
put into a backpack and tie with a rope
to their feet so that as they Crawl
Through the tight spaces of the cave
they have to pull this battery pack
along with them that runs the helium
neon laser power to the Head
um this was the greatest thing to come
down the pike for them this guy now has
something that may weigh two ounces that
you can put in his pocket and take it in
with him and him and his wife can you
Holograms inside the cave without
worrying about the helium neon laser and
the power supply that has to go with it
because imagine that battery pack must
have some weight to it to drag that
thing through a cave not that you get me
in a cave to begin with anyone
and this opened holography to many new
people which is what we need we need
more people doing Holograms and finally
finally we have something
that will allow people to do that
it needs holography needs a good shot in
the arm with new Young talented
practitioners you need some mutants new
ideas I think this is one of the ways
that we can at least at least have them
take that first initial step where it's
not going to break the bank and if they
don't like it
they haven't put out a large amount of
money
and lost it
who cares
who cares if you spend eight bucks and
you get some chemistry or borrow some
chemistry from a photography friend and
set something up and start to shoot a
couple programs to see if you like it
you can always move on go out and get
that 30 millilitini or that 20 watt
Argon
but you have to start somewhere and this
is the perfect
place to start
not to mention schools on real tight
budgets teachers they don't always have
money you know schools they don't have
any money
especially for Sciences you know I want
to get on that kick
but sciences and things are you know
there's no money for that
no money for that
I won't say where the money goes
when I start trouble
now what can we do with these laser
pointers well there's different types of
holograms that can be made
so far
we've got single beam laser transmission
and reflection Holograms
and I know I remember reading quite a
few articles about a technique to do
single beam white light transmission
Holograms
along with white light transmission
Holograms that you do not have to do a
slip Master first
so I will continue to look into that I
have not had the time to go through the
back issues I believe it may have been
in either laser news or holosphere
one of those Publications that goes back
probably to the late 80s or so I believe
I'll find it but I haven't I haven't had
the time to look
and it's possible to do a split thing
let me tell you something I burnt one of
these diodes out I wanted to see it's
you know eight bucks I figured let's
let's see what this baby can take so I
got the power supply and I've got
different settings on there you know
three volts 4.5 6 volts uh Seven
Something eight ten twelve I think I got
up to around 10 or 12 before I saw that
that white uh puff of smoke come out and
the thing black out on me
uh so what I did is I figured well this
baby shot so I got the second one that I
bought and opened that up and hooked it
up to the power supply made sure I kept
the power at 4.5 volts this time and
I'll tell you something this second
one's a lot brighter than the other one
was so there must be some sort of a
variation in the actual power output
sometimes of these diodes but I'll tell
you something I've worked I began
holography with a five milliwatt back in
when I started the studio in 1983 from
Aerotech
which was out let me see how well my
memory serves me Zetta v e t a vetta
Drive Pittsburgh Pennsylvania and I
think I paid
for a
five know a lot that was self-contained
tube and power supply in a cylindrical
housing I believe that was what it was
and if memory serves me right I'm
looking over at the table right now
I think this is just as bright as that
five milowatts heating this little laser
diode that I have on here right now is
screaming it's really screaming so I I'm
going to try and do a split the Hologram
using this laser and that of course will
open things up to other things as well
this is what's so exciting about it this
is what's so exciting is because all the
adventure's still there I mean it's a
whole new road that hasn't yet been
traveled you know I don't need a 20 watt
argon to make me happy this stuff is
what's hot right now this is exciting
this is exciting
and of course some Advanced Techniques
now remember you can do multiple color
holography using a single wavelength
it's done way back in the early 80s or
mid 80s
probably one of the first names that
comes to mind doing that work is John
Kaufman
and multi-color using triathanolamine
and all of these techniques can be found
just about any holography book so you've
got your five milliwatt laser diode uh
you ready to do your hologram and if you
want to start experimenting with a
number of different things that could be
considered a little bit more advanced
work you can get into the triathlonian
technique and start doing some multiple
colors single beam Holograms if if it
turns out that the split beans just a
little bit too much from these diodes
right now
and who knows what's coming down the
pike
who knows how long is it going to be
before we have a 25 milliwatt 650 640
635 nanometer diode
that's
one but
that's something
of course
eight by ten is a question and just like
I had mentioned that I think this
Laser's a little bit more powerful than
the first one I had in there judging
from my eyes and what I see as far as a
spread over a four by five area that I
have set up right now
I think it may be possible
to do a single beam eight by ten
if it's a good system good table good
solid table it's not going to bend and
twist and not getting a lot of vibration
I think it may be possible to do it and
all these things are coming up boy
wow what are the drawbacks well I guess
you know that action materials are hard
to find we are working with some
materials that are less sensitive than
what the agfa was and what this works
out to be is actually longer exposure
times longer exposure times and you can
get around that four by five Holograms
are no problem with this laser diode
this is I'm reading from notes that are
actually a little bit further down on
the page but my exposure time for this
4x5 plate
was four seconds and I was going by I
used the science and mechanics meter and
the holography handbook basically the
chart that's in there for single beans
when I do them
and I was getting a 10 reading on a two
scale
which worked out to I believe it may
have been two seconds
and of course I always double that for
reflection Holograms
so
if you have some materials that you have
to buy that are less sensitive than the
AG for 8075 HD
make smaller Holograms you know
go smaller
you can still make them get started
now the Hologram I made
way it makes no hold on without jumping
ahead
that's the difference if you've got a
five millilit we've got a five milliwatt
diode you still working with five
milliwatts so you're still going to have
the same problem with each one so you
either have a problem with something
you've paid 200 for or you're going to
have a problem with something you paid
7.99 for good choice
like I said I made a single beam
reflection hologram it was four by five
on an axa8075 HD glass plate was Frosty
the Snowman and that's another funny
thing you see on test Holograms
holographers must just run around the
house or run around the studio and just
pick up anything that they see to put in
there because a lot of the test
Holograms that I've seen was like you
know there were absolutely no thought
going into anything
including this one I mean Frosty the
Snowman what does that say nothing but
you grab whatever you can grab because I
think a lot of times you're just in a
hurry and excited to get a shot off
the exposure time was four seconds and
that's using the chart in the holography
handbook it was a 10 reading on a 2
scale
uh it was spatial filter I sent the
light through a spatial filter now Steve
Michael said he was having problems with
his laser sending it through a spatial
filter because of the elliptical beam
profile that came out of the diode
I believe in the Leisure that I have has
collimating Optics in here because I get
a beautiful dot on the wall I it goes
through the spatial filter with
absolutely no problem at all and it's a
beautiful spread
of a wave front of light coming out of
that spatial filter and what I'm going
to have to do is I'm going to have to
get some photographs taken with the
digital camera or whatever just to show
you the quality of what's happening with
this with these layered laser diodes
because you know seeing is believing
that development was d19
developer and the bleach was the
standard anything goes potassium bromide
potassium ferrocyanide bleach
bleach that I just happen to have mixed
that was old it was really old I think
it may have been left over from
summertime or something like that but I
didn't want to mix anything new up I'm
going to get back in
lab and start with some Pyro
the pyrochrome process and which I'm a
little bit more familiar working with
with the reflection Holograms
but in any case there you have it folks
what we have on top view this week I
called L Michael Roberts who is the
webmaster at Laser FX and he deals a lot
with laser legislation and he a contact
person for the laser industry in the
press and he was nice enough to come on
the show and give some comments on the
legislation and law
behind laser diodes and just as a
coincidence I'm driving home tonight and
it says that near Rendell is signing a
bill into law in Philadelphia that you
have to be 18 years old to purchase a
laser pointer in Philadelphia and they
also are going to there's a bill that's
been introduced to legislate its use
and that's all I could get out of it so
if I can get some more information as
far as what they mean by that
legislating its use
I'll get some more information but
wouldn't that be funny if all of a
sudden
the only thing that these stupid laser
pointers were used for was to go to
concerts and try and hit the singer in
the eye or whatever everybody's doing
with these things out there
and all of a sudden it comes along that
for very reasonable amount of money
actually almost a fantasy amount of
money some people still don't believe it
yet
that you can create three-dimensional
laser Holograms and these things can
actually turn people onto a field that
they may pursue later on in college
physics Optics
and all of a sudden
they're gone you can't even get them
anymore I don't think that's going to
happen
by a bunch of them folks I think they
have a life of like a hundred thousand
hours so get them now
stock up
and also this week we'll be playing the
Steve Michael interview the original
interview and just to show how fast the
world is moving
it's old news already but there's so
many requests to hear it that I'm
putting it up again and I hope you enjoy
it it was certainly a pleasure doing it
I've been in contact a few times since
with Steve Michael both by email and on
the phone and we're going to continue
with this we're going to continue
pushing it because it's just an
absolutely incredible thing I'm just so
excited about it
so thank you for tuning in this week
I'm taking some time off
the next show will be January 10th I'm
going to be replaying I had a couple
requests for some shows like the
holographic heart that's going to go up
I believe in a week so I've had some
requests to do a few repeats so I'll put
those on while I'm on holiday and I want
to thank everyone for tuning in
and I hope you're as excited about this
as I am even if you're working in a lab
with a 20 watt argon come on be excited
this is really exciting stuff
it really is where's the little kid in
you especially this time of year it's so
magical you know to be down here working
with this again and it's so much
Discovery involved and then I go
upstairs and it's all Christmas lights
and Christmas trees and all the Sparkle
and all this other kind of stuff what a
perfect time of the year for this to
happen it's really nice so thank you for
tuning in this is Frankie Freitas have a
great holiday season have a great new
year 1999 last year of this century
wow also a great time of the century for
this to happen too boy this is
holography 21st century
so take care and I'll see you next year
God willing it's been an honor being
your host on this show for a season and
a half and I look forward to continue
doing this and continuing to allow it to
grow and evolve into whatever it is that
grows and evolves into take care this is
Frankie Freitas for holotalk